<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.1.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-01-13T13:03:41+01:00</updated><id>/</id><title>Oliver Westerwinter</title><subtitle>I am an Assistant Professor of Political Science at the Department of Political Science at the University of St. Gallen. On this website, you find information about my research and teaching.</subtitle><author><name>Oliver Westerwinter, PhD</name><email>oliver.westerwinter@unisg.ch</email></author><entry><title>Measuring Transnational Public-Private Governance Initiatives in World Politics: A New Dataset</title><link href="/working%20paper/Measuring-Transnational-Public-Private-Governance-Initiatives-in-World-Politics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Measuring Transnational Public-Private Governance Initiatives in World Politics: A New Dataset" /><published>2017-01-11T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-01-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/working%20paper/Measuring-Transnational-Public-Private-Governance-Initiatives-in-World-Politics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/working%20paper/Measuring-Transnational-Public-Private-Governance-Initiatives-in-World-Politics/">&lt;p&gt;This paper summarizes the Transnational Public-Private Governance Initiatives in World Politics Data. The data contains detailed information on the scope, membership, and institutional
design of 481 transnational publi-private governance initiatives (TGIs) in which states and/or
formal intergovernmental organizations cooperate with business and civil society actors to
govern global problems. I provide detailed descriptions of the sample generation and discuss
coding rules. I also map the development of TGIs at the initiative and state level of analysis
and show how the new data contributes to enhancing researchers’ understanding of transnational public-private governance. The paper concludes by identifying puzzles and avenues for
future research on transnational public-private governance in world politics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oliver Westerwinter, PhD</name><email>oliver.westerwinter@unisg.ch</email></author><category term="[&quot;Working paper&quot;]" /><summary>This paper summarizes the Transnational Public-Private Governance Initiatives in World Politics Data. The data contains detailed information on the scope, membership, and institutional
design of 481 transnational publi-private governance initiatives (TGIs) in which states and/or
formal intergovernmental organizations cooperate with business and civil society actors to
govern global problems. I provide detailed descriptions of the sample generation and discuss
coding rules. I also map the development of TGIs at the initiative and state level of analysis
and show how the new data contributes to enhancing researchers’ understanding of transnational public-private governance. The paper concludes by identifying puzzles and avenues for
future research on transnational public-private governance in world politics.</summary></entry><entry><title>Power or Domestic Politics? Explaining State Participation in Informal International Institutions</title><link href="/research/Power-or-Domestic-Politics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Power or Domestic Politics? Explaining State Participation in Informal International Institutions" /><published>2016-12-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-12-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/research/Power-or-Domestic-Politics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/research/Power-or-Domestic-Politics/">&lt;p&gt;Why have states recently started to use informal institutions instead of formal organizations to govern global policy issues? What factors drive states’ decisions to join informal international institutions? Extant research on the forms of institutionalization in global governance focuses on formal modes of cooperation, such as intergovernmental organizations and treaties. Formal rules, however, do not exhaust the institutional variety of international cooperation. They are often inadequate, if not entirely misleading, descriptions of the game that actors play in world politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent work in political science, economics, and international law has started to examine informal governance as a mode of international cooperation. Informal governance refers to unwritten (and often vaguely specified) rules, shared expectations, and norms that are not enshrined in formally constituted organizations and which modify or substitute legally binding rules. It includes informal practices within formal intergovernmental organizations, informal institutions, and a broad array of networks constituted by state and non-state actors. Examples include: informal intergovernmental organizations, such as the G8; and transnational governance initiatives of states, companies, and non-governmental organizations, such as the Kimberley Process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether focused on formal or informal institutions, existing scholarship reflects only small portions of the institutional architecture of contemporary global governance in isolation. Yet, as long as we do not take into account the wider spectrum of institutional variation, our analyses of the determinants of states’ institutional choices at the global level remain partial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed project examines the factors that lead states to choose between formal intergovernmental organizations (FIGOs), informal intergovernmental organizations (IIGOs), and transnational governance initiatives (TGIs) to structure their interactions and to govern global problems. We also investigate the role that the design of informal international institutions plays in states decisions to join them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We argue that power and domestic politics are critical for explaining the striking variation in states’ participation in informal global governance. Governments use informal international institutions as a means to project power and bias outcomes toward their particularistic interests. They also use informal modes of cooperation to bypass domestic institutional constrains that make achieving outcomes in-line with their preferences costly or impossible. We test hypotheses derived from our theoretical argument using statistical analysis and our extension of a new dataset on formal and informal international institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our expected results are relevant for scholars and practitioners alike. On the one hand, our systematic account of the institutional choices of states goes beyond existing work on informal governance within FIGOs as well as the established research on international institutional design. On the other hand, obtaining accurate knowledge about the factors that shape states’ participation in informal international cooperation helps policy-makers to effectively provide public goods and enhance the legitimacy, equity, and efficiency of global governance institutions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oliver Westerwinter, PhD</name><email>oliver.westerwinter@unisg.ch</email></author><category term="Research" /><summary>Why have states recently started to use informal institutions instead of formal organizations to govern global policy issues? What factors drive states’ decisions to join informal international institutions? Extant research on the forms of institutionalization in global governance focuses on formal modes of cooperation, such as intergovernmental organizations and treaties. Formal rules, however, do not exhaust the institutional variety of international cooperation. They are often inadequate, if not entirely misleading, descriptions of the game that actors play in world politics.</summary></entry><entry><title>The Politics of Informal Governance</title><link href="/working%20paper/The-Politics-of-Informal-Governance/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Politics of Informal Governance" /><published>2016-11-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-11-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/working%20paper/The-Politics-of-Informal-Governance</id><content type="html" xml:base="/working%20paper/The-Politics-of-Informal-Governance/">&lt;p&gt;Why do states sometimes use informal instead of formal institutions to govern global problems? Extant research on the forms of institutionalization in world politics focuses on formal
modes of cooperation, such as intergovernmental organizations and treaties. Formal rules,
however, do not exhaust the institutional variety of international cooperation. They are often
inadequate, if not entirely misleading, descriptions of the game that actors play in world politics. Recent work in political science has started to examine informal governance as a mode
of cooperation in global governance. In this paper, I examine the factors that lead states to
choose between formal intergovernmental organizations, informal intergovernmental organizations, and transnational public-private governance initiatives to structure their interactions
and govern global problems. I highlight the political dimensions of informal governance and
argue that distributional conict and power asymmetries are critical for the selection and
design of informal modes of international cooperation. States use informal institutions as
a means to project power and bias outcomes toward their particularistic interests. Using a
new dataset on formal and informal international institutions, I test hypotheses derived from
this argument as well as alternative functionalist explanations. Results indicate that power
dynamics are a strong driver of the emergence of informal international institutions, while
functionalist factors are of less importance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oliver Westerwinter, PhD</name><email>oliver.westerwinter@unisg.ch</email></author><category term="[&quot;Working paper&quot;]" /><summary>Why do states sometimes use informal instead of formal institutions to govern global problems? Extant research on the forms of institutionalization in world politics focuses on formal
modes of cooperation, such as intergovernmental organizations and treaties. Formal rules,
however, do not exhaust the institutional variety of international cooperation. They are often
inadequate, if not entirely misleading, descriptions of the game that actors play in world politics. Recent work in political science has started to examine informal governance as a mode
of cooperation in global governance. In this paper, I examine the factors that lead states to
choose between formal intergovernmental organizations, informal intergovernmental organizations, and transnational public-private governance initiatives to structure their interactions
and govern global problems. I highlight the political dimensions of informal governance and
argue that distributional conict and power asymmetries are critical for the selection and
design of informal modes of international cooperation. States use informal institutions as
a means to project power and bias outcomes toward their particularistic interests. Using a
new dataset on formal and informal international institutions, I test hypotheses derived from
this argument as well as alternative functionalist explanations. Results indicate that power
dynamics are a strong driver of the emergence of informal international institutions, while
functionalist factors are of less importance.</summary></entry><entry><title>Multiplex Choices: Intra- and Inter-Network Dependencies and the Formation of Military Alliances</title><link href="/working%20paper/Intra-and-Inter-Network-Dependencies-and-the-Formation-of-Military-Alliances/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Multiplex Choices: Intra- and Inter-Network Dependencies and the Formation of Military Alliances" /><published>2016-11-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-11-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/working%20paper/Intra-and-Inter-Network-Dependencies-and-the-Formation-of-Military-Alliances</id><content type="html" xml:base="/working%20paper/Intra-and-Inter-Network-Dependencies-and-the-Formation-of-Military-Alliances/">&lt;p&gt;The formation, maintenance, and dissolution of military alliances is the result of strategic
interaction among nations. In this paper, I argue that states’ alliance behavior is not only
aected by characteristics of countries and dyads, but also by the behavior of other dyads
in the alliance network. I also maintain that patterns of cooperation in other international
networks, such as those constituted by states’ shared memberships in intergovernmental organizations (IGOs), have inuence on how alliances are formed. To estimate these within
and cross-network extra-dyadic interdependencies, I use temporal exponential random graph
models. This allows to avoid the assumption of independence of observations which underlies
the vast majority of estimation techniques employed by international relations scholars and to
directly model interdependence eects of triadic and higher order within and across networks.
I test my argument using data on international alliances from 1950 to 1992. Results suggest
that both within and cross-network extra-dyadic dependencies exercise powerful inuence on
states’ alliance choices indicating that strategic interaction does neither stop at the dyad nor
at the network level of analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oliver Westerwinter, PhD</name><email>oliver.westerwinter@unisg.ch</email></author><category term="[&quot;Working paper&quot;]" /><summary>The formation, maintenance, and dissolution of military alliances is the result of strategic
interaction among nations. In this paper, I argue that states’ alliance behavior is not only
aected by characteristics of countries and dyads, but also by the behavior of other dyads
in the alliance network. I also maintain that patterns of cooperation in other international
networks, such as those constituted by states’ shared memberships in intergovernmental organizations (IGOs), have inuence on how alliances are formed. To estimate these within
and cross-network extra-dyadic interdependencies, I use temporal exponential random graph
models. This allows to avoid the assumption of independence of observations which underlies
the vast majority of estimation techniques employed by international relations scholars and to
directly model interdependence eects of triadic and higher order within and across networks.
I test my argument using data on international alliances from 1950 to 1992. Results suggest
that both within and cross-network extra-dyadic dependencies exercise powerful inuence on
states’ alliance choices indicating that strategic interaction does neither stop at the dyad nor
at the network level of analysis.</summary></entry><entry><title>Uncertainty, Network Change, and Costly Signaling: How the Network of Diplomatic Visits Affects the Initiation of International Conflict</title><link href="/working%20paper/Uncertainty-Network-Change-and-Costly-Signaling/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Uncertainty, Network Change, and Costly Signaling: How the Network of Diplomatic Visits Affects the Initiation of International Conflict" /><published>2016-10-20T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-10-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/working%20paper/Uncertainty-Network-Change-and-Costly-Signaling</id><content type="html" xml:base="/working%20paper/Uncertainty-Network-Change-and-Costly-Signaling/">&lt;p&gt;Bargaining theories of war emphasize the role of private information as a fundamental cause of conflict.
Leaders are uncertain about one another’s military strength, preferences, and trustworthiness and, as a
result, can miscalculate the expected costs and outcomes of fighting which may lead to the outbreak of
conflict. Thus, a critical step in the onset of conflict is determining what leaders are likely to know and
where they get their information from. I argue that what state leaders know is the result of their embeddedness
in international networks with other leaders. These networks can serve as an infrastructure
for information exchange and, more importantly, as a costly and credible signaling device. First, government
agents of states may communicate with representatives of other states to obtain strategic information
about potential opponents. Second, state leaders may use their pattern of interactions with other
leaders to publicly disseminate costly signals about their preferences and demonstrate trustworthiness
and alliances. In other words, international networks can function as direct and indirect communication
mechanisms. I argue that states’ positions and changes of positions in these direct, and particularly indirect,
international communication structures affect uncertainty and the probability of conflict initiation.
Using data on diplomatic visits of government agents from 1990 to 2004 and employing network statistics
to measure changes in the similarity of states’ positions in the diplomatic visits network, I show that
states’ positions in the diplomatic visits networks are a powerful predictor of conflict initiation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oliver Westerwinter, PhD</name><email>oliver.westerwinter@unisg.ch</email></author><category term="[&quot;Working paper&quot;]" /><summary>Bargaining theories of war emphasize the role of private information as a fundamental cause of conflict.
Leaders are uncertain about one another’s military strength, preferences, and trustworthiness and, as a
result, can miscalculate the expected costs and outcomes of fighting which may lead to the outbreak of
conflict. Thus, a critical step in the onset of conflict is determining what leaders are likely to know and
where they get their information from. I argue that what state leaders know is the result of their embeddedness
in international networks with other leaders. These networks can serve as an infrastructure
for information exchange and, more importantly, as a costly and credible signaling device. First, government
agents of states may communicate with representatives of other states to obtain strategic information
about potential opponents. Second, state leaders may use their pattern of interactions with other
leaders to publicly disseminate costly signals about their preferences and demonstrate trustworthiness
and alliances. In other words, international networks can function as direct and indirect communication
mechanisms. I argue that states’ positions and changes of positions in these direct, and particularly indirect,
international communication structures affect uncertainty and the probability of conflict initiation.
Using data on diplomatic visits of government agents from 1990 to 2004 and employing network statistics
to measure changes in the similarity of states’ positions in the diplomatic visits network, I show that
states’ positions in the diplomatic visits networks are a powerful predictor of conflict initiation.</summary></entry><entry><title>New Power Politics</title><link href="/books/New-Power-Politics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Power Politics" /><published>2016-07-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-07-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/books/New-Power-Politics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/books/New-Power-Politics/">&lt;p&gt;Traditional analyses of global security cannot explain the degree to which there is “governance” of important security issues — from combatting piracy to curtailing nuclear proliferation to reducing the contributions of extractive industries to violence and conflict. They are even less able to explain why contemporary governance schemes involve the various actors and take the many forms they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Juxtaposing the insights of scholars writing about new modes of governance with the logic of network theory, The New Power Politics offers a framework for understanding contemporary security governance and its variation. The framework rests on a fresh view of power and how it works in global politics. Though power is integral to governance, it is something that emerges from, and depends on, relationships. Thus, power is dynamic; it is something that governors must continually cultivate with a wide range of consequential global players, and how a governor uses power in one situation can have consequences for her future relationships, and thus, future power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding this new power politics is crucial for explaining and shaping the future of global security politics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oliver Westerwinter, PhD</name><email>oliver.westerwinter@unisg.ch</email></author><category term="Books" /><summary>Traditional analyses of global security cannot explain the degree to which there is “governance” of important security issues — from combatting piracy to curtailing nuclear proliferation to reducing the contributions of extractive industries to violence and conflict. They are even less able to explain why contemporary governance schemes involve the various actors and take the many forms they do.</summary></entry><entry><title>The Evolution of Transnational Governance Interactions: A Network Approach</title><link href="/working%20paper/Evolution-of-Transnational-Governance-Interactions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Evolution of Transnational Governance Interactions: A Network Approach" /><published>2016-05-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-05-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/working%20paper/Evolution-of-Transnational-Governance-Interactions</id><content type="html" xml:base="/working%20paper/Evolution-of-Transnational-Governance-Interactions/">&lt;p&gt;Transnational public-private governance initiatives (TGIs) in which governments, business,
and non-governmental organizations (NGOs) cooperate to regulate the negative externalities
of global corporate and state conduct have become an important element of world politics. In
a broad range of issue areas, TGIs co-exist with other TGIs. This co-existence of governance
arrangements creates ample room for inter-institutional interactions. However, while in some
issue areas the interactions among TGIs have been rapidly growing over time, in others they
have been characterized by a more mixed pattern of growth and decline, and in still others
they have remained at a low level throughout. In addition, we observe wide variation in the
quality of interactions among TGIs as well as between TGIs and other forms of governance,
ranging from coordination and cooperation to competition for participants, resources, and
inuence. In this paper, I use a network approach to empirically model the factors underlying
the evolution of interactions among TGIs across issue areas and over time. The data for my
analysis comes from a new dataset on international cooperation that includes detailed information on more than 250 TGIs in a broad range of issue areas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oliver Westerwinter, PhD</name><email>oliver.westerwinter@unisg.ch</email></author><category term="[&quot;Working paper&quot;]" /><summary>Transnational public-private governance initiatives (TGIs) in which governments, business,
and non-governmental organizations (NGOs) cooperate to regulate the negative externalities
of global corporate and state conduct have become an important element of world politics. In
a broad range of issue areas, TGIs co-exist with other TGIs. This co-existence of governance
arrangements creates ample room for inter-institutional interactions. However, while in some
issue areas the interactions among TGIs have been rapidly growing over time, in others they
have been characterized by a more mixed pattern of growth and decline, and in still others
they have remained at a low level throughout. In addition, we observe wide variation in the
quality of interactions among TGIs as well as between TGIs and other forms of governance,
ranging from coordination and cooperation to competition for participants, resources, and
inuence. In this paper, I use a network approach to empirically model the factors underlying
the evolution of interactions among TGIs across issue areas and over time. The data for my
analysis comes from a new dataset on international cooperation that includes detailed information on more than 250 TGIs in a broad range of issue areas.</summary></entry><entry><title>Networked international politics: Complex interdependence and the diffusion of conflict and peace</title><link href="/papers/Networked-international-politics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Networked international politics: Complex interdependence and the diffusion of conflict and peace" /><published>2016-03-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-03-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/papers/Networked-international-politics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/papers/Networked-international-politics/">&lt;p&gt;Network theory and methods are becoming increasingly used to study the causes and consequences of conflict. Network analysis allows researchers to develop a better understanding of the causal dynamics and structural geometry of the complex web of interdependencies at work in the onset, incidence, and diffusion of conflict and peace. This issue features new theoretical and empirical research demonstrating how properly accounting for networked interdependencies has profound implications for our understanding of the processes thought to be responsible for the conflict behavior of state and non-state actors. The contributors examine the variation in networks of states and transnational actors to explain outcomes related to international conflict and peace. They highlight how networked interdependencies affect conflict and cooperation in a broad range of areas at the center of international relations scholarship. It is helpful to distinguish between three uses of networks, namely: (1) as theoretical tools, (2) as measurement tools, and (3) as inferential tools. The introduction discusses each of these uses and shows how the contributions rely on one or several of them. Next, Monte Carlo simulations are used to illustrate one of the strengths of network analysis, namely that it helps researchers avoid biased inferences when the data generating process underlying the observed data contains extradyadic interdependencies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oliver Westerwinter, PhD</name><email>oliver.westerwinter@unisg.ch</email></author><category term="[&quot;Papers&quot;]" /><summary>Network theory and methods are becoming increasingly used to study the causes and consequences of conflict. Network analysis allows researchers to develop a better understanding of the causal dynamics and structural geometry of the complex web of interdependencies at work in the onset, incidence, and diffusion of conflict and peace. This issue features new theoretical and empirical research demonstrating how properly accounting for networked interdependencies has profound implications for our understanding of the processes thought to be responsible for the conflict behavior of state and non-state actors. The contributors examine the variation in networks of states and transnational actors to explain outcomes related to international conflict and peace. They highlight how networked interdependencies affect conflict and cooperation in a broad range of areas at the center of international relations scholarship. It is helpful to distinguish between three uses of networks, namely: (1) as theoretical tools, (2) as measurement tools, and (3) as inferential tools. The introduction discusses each of these uses and shows how the contributions rely on one or several of them. Next, Monte Carlo simulations are used to illustrate one of the strengths of network analysis, namely that it helps researchers avoid biased inferences when the data generating process underlying the observed data contains extradyadic interdependencies.</summary></entry><entry><title>The complex structure of commercial peace contrasting trade interdependence, asymmetry, and multipolarity</title><link href="/papers/The-Complex-Structure/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The complex structure of commercial peace contrasting trade interdependence, asymmetry, and multipolarity" /><published>2016-03-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-03-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/papers/The-Complex-Structure</id><content type="html" xml:base="/papers/The-Complex-Structure/">&lt;p&gt;Researchers continue to debate the impact of trade on interstate conflict. While many view trade as pacifying, others argue that dependencies increase friction and the risk of war. We provide a theory that explains how cross-border economic ties alternately enhance or impede international cooperation. Three main factors account for the heterogeneous effects of trade on conflict: interdependence, asymmetry, and multipolarity. Interdependence can act as a substitute for, or as a deterrent to, militarized violence. In the former case, interdependence actually increases more modest non-militarized conflict, while also discouraging militarized disputes. Asymmetry diminishes the conflict-inhibiting effect of trade ties, as dependency cannot simultaneously be used to coerce and to inform. Multilateral trade networks alternately moderate or enhance the bilateral effects of interdependence and asymmetry on interstate peace. Our theory and evidence reveal complex, cross-cutting consequences of economic interdependence on conflict behavior and also demonstrate effects well beyond the dyad, suggesting the need to include extradyadic ties in future theoretical and empirical research studying the commercial peace.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oliver Westerwinter, PhD</name><email>oliver.westerwinter@unisg.ch</email></author><category term="Papers" /><summary>Researchers continue to debate the impact of trade on interstate conflict. While many view trade as pacifying, others argue that dependencies increase friction and the risk of war. We provide a theory that explains how cross-border economic ties alternately enhance or impede international cooperation. Three main factors account for the heterogeneous effects of trade on conflict: interdependence, asymmetry, and multipolarity. Interdependence can act as a substitute for, or as a deterrent to, militarized violence. In the former case, interdependence actually increases more modest non-militarized conflict, while also discouraging militarized disputes. Asymmetry diminishes the conflict-inhibiting effect of trade ties, as dependency cannot simultaneously be used to coerce and to inform. Multilateral trade networks alternately moderate or enhance the bilateral effects of interdependence and asymmetry on interstate peace. Our theory and evidence reveal complex, cross-cutting consequences of economic interdependence on conflict behavior and also demonstrate effects well beyond the dyad, suggesting the need to include extradyadic ties in future theoretical and empirical research studying the commercial peace.</summary></entry><entry><title>Co-Evolution of Depth, Flexibility, and Enforcement in Trade Agreements: A Network Approach</title><link href="/%0Agovernance.md/working%20paper/Co-Evolution-of-Depth-Flexibility-and-Enforcement-in-Trade-Agreements/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Co-Evolution of Depth, Flexibility, and Enforcement in Trade Agreements: A Network Approach" /><published>2015-06-25T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-06-25T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/%0Agovernance.md/working%20paper/Co-Evolution-of-Depth-Flexibility-and-Enforcement-in-Trade-Agreements</id><content type="html" xml:base="/%0Agovernance.md/working%20paper/Co-Evolution-of-Depth-Flexibility-and-Enforcement-in-Trade-Agreements/">&lt;p&gt;Over the past ten years a large number of studies has explored the diusion of bilateral
and regional economic agreements. A related stream of research has formally theorized and
empirically demonstrated the interdependence between dierent dimensions of the design of
international institutions, in particular, the positive correlation between depth and exibility.
We make a rst attempt to link these two literatures. Our argument is that trade-related
regulations diuse from one preferential trade agreement (PTA) to another as a result of
competition among states. The resulting diusion of depth-related provisions simultaneously
impacts also the exibility and enforcement dimensions of PTA design. Concretely, countries
that adopt deep trade-related regulations from competitors also have incentives to include escape clauses to mitigate costs of compliance and dispute mechanisms to stabilize cooperation.
We test our hypotheses using an original dataset on the design of 587 PTAs from 1985 to 2009
and relying on statistical network analysis. Our paper contributes to the literatures on international cooperation, the political economy of trade, and the rational design of international
institutions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oliver Westerwinter, PhD</name><email>oliver.westerwinter@unisg.ch</email></author><category term="[&quot;Working paper&quot;]" /><summary>Over the past ten years a large number of studies has explored the diusion of bilateral
and regional economic agreements. A related stream of research has formally theorized and
empirically demonstrated the interdependence between dierent dimensions of the design of
international institutions, in particular, the positive correlation between depth and exibility.
We make a rst attempt to link these two literatures. Our argument is that trade-related
regulations diuse from one preferential trade agreement (PTA) to another as a result of
competition among states. The resulting diusion of depth-related provisions simultaneously
impacts also the exibility and enforcement dimensions of PTA design. Concretely, countries
that adopt deep trade-related regulations from competitors also have incentives to include escape clauses to mitigate costs of compliance and dispute mechanisms to stabilize cooperation.
We test our hypotheses using an original dataset on the design of 587 PTAs from 1985 to 2009
and relying on statistical network analysis. Our paper contributes to the literatures on international cooperation, the political economy of trade, and the rational design of international
institutions.</summary></entry></feed>
